[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's generally referring to, like, the senses, but also then, kind of, what the senses disclose.
Like, I was thinking about, like, how I disclose, for example, like, space and distance and stuff through the senses, and trying to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'll just read to you what I wrote, and you can stop me anytime.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I wrote, the senses can be discerned as a point of view or an orientation regarding things.
[SPEAKER_02]: The working sense base allows for the disclosure of a respective field or a respective world of visual objects, of sounds, etc.
[SPEAKER_02]: There must absolutely be this point of view for there to be experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: To have no point of view or every point of
Furthermore, the position of this point of view corresponds with the location of that respective matter as disclosed through other senses.
Though one must be sure to remember that this is not the matter itself, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can touch my eyeball, but that is a perception of touch, not the eye, which is that by which there is vision.
Hence, the senses are negative phenomena.
They do not appear, but the fact that there is a presentation within limits allows for their discernment.
The senses then also disclose space, such as in the form of distance, area, and so on.
Thus, I can designate a near or far, or a here or yon
This here, by appropriating senses, becomes me in terms of a spatial positioning.
I am here.
Things are there.
I am internal.
Everything else is external.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the cessation of that appropriation, things still stand in the world, but now simply, simply seen as a conscious six-based body and name and form externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, nothing to add or subtract.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to say, when you started, I was about to say, uh, you have to point out that senses do not appear, but then you pointed it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just, I just was on a, like, a tangent at one point, where it's kind of like, how do I know that the senses are there if they don't appear?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's their thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you can kind of, it's an inference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you can know.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I was just kind of working on that word, like, as point of view, instead of kind of using the designation senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a point of view, because it's already... anything that's directed, which anything that's conscious, it's already directed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever there's consciousness, there's a direction, which means there's a point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, and senses in themselves, they have their own direction of senses towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, absolutely, that is what point of view is.
One other thing I was also thinking about is, like, in terms of mind, I was trying to kind of sort out my ideas on what mind as mano versus mind as citta.
Now, I understand in some basic sense that mano is like
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say, that by which I can imagine things, or, you know, imaginary objects, real as such.
So, in that kind of sense, though, is there some overlap between that, like, let's say, you know, a thought of a feeling, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that something that appears in the senses, that how one could describe that, or is it different?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean, thought of a feeling?
Like, like a person, like a, you know, I think, oh, such a feeling is present as a thought.
Uh-huh.
And as one could describe it, then, as like, so to say, a mind object with the mind sense base.
Yes.
Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, but citta refers to something different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what's that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, citta refers to the actual feeling that's being felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simultaneous presence of sañña and vedanā.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what citta is, in regards to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: The peripheral of that, he said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say another.
[SPEAKER_00]: But simultaneous presence
[SPEAKER_00]: With the presence of sañña, chā, vedanā, khandhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're simultaneous, to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to the extent of feeling being felt, perception being perceived, the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of the mind as a...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not actually inaccurate to translate it as heart, as Enereta mentioned once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it involves feelings, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: The citta is inconceivable without feelings being felt, perceptions perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the mind on that level, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you can... by the way, I don't want to say hard, because then... it brings notions of self-indulgence.
[SPEAKER_00]: All kinds of kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's certainly... it's certainly... well, you can say it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a completely different phenomenon, but it's also, as such, it is quite more of a negative, more general than māna in itself would be, the actual thinking, in terms of the mind objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, when it comes to citta, it's more passive in that regard, in comparison to māna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the moods, the states of mind, elated mind, depressed mind, mind with joy, equanimous mind, kind of very, very general states, you discern as something that has a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just find it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means those moods are of a very general nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And basically,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can't be actively, so to speak, involved on that level, in as much as you could be with actually choosing what you want to think, yeah, in terms of the mind objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's probably important to distinguish, because people are mind-mind, and then, when the moods are present, or some quite a quite a general kind of feelings and ambiguous perceptions, they even regard that in the same sense as if you as if you would regard it thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, actually, often people dismiss it as well, to themselves, as just abstract thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they can't, they can't concede it in any other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if they're all in front of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, citta is more of something that's being felt, and obviously simultaneously perceived at that general level, in its ambiguous notion, like a notion of expansion, a notion of trunk, a notion of light, a notion of heavy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the perceptions in regard to citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the endeavor.
Can one
Like, and say, you know, we use the term accessible, inaccessible, in terms of, like, rūpa, especially.
Uh-huh.
Could we say something similar with citta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that, you know, whenever I... there's a mood of the mind that says, all I ever can have... You can say basically the same in regard to the whole five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're really inaccessible to you, in their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing that, you access it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop upādāna in regard to it, and you assume it.
So, I think I'm in a bad mood, but that thought is not the mood itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you don't know what the mood itself is, that thought, which is actually not the mood itself, is the only thing that stands for that mood for you in that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you assumed, you assumed it, and it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I was thinking too about, like, in terms of sense basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a... it seems to me, in some sense, how to put this, some, like, so to say, different view required, like, for the mind, as opposed to, like, the eye.
Because, like, even with it back to the
Well, yeah.
I mean, there is now so much of a defined distance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the distance is very much there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The space is very much there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: Primarily, space is mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what a space is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the movement is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The notion of movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if nothing moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how space is being generated, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how, because of that, you can see it in things, around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is, it is, that's why, that's why space can be used.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's always often described as one of
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, after the four great elements, then the element of space, then the element of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although it's not a fundamental one, it almost is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's so impersonal, obviously.
Yeah, and they have that base of infinite space, too.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I found that all curious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, it's, you know, there is plenty of things to be contemplated on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by it as a negative?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the space without the object is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no such thing as a pure space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the infinite space, it's the infinite negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you step into it negatively.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't take it up as an object, which is a positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on a more simple level, let's say, space disclosed through my eye.
Well, space is disclosed by mind in regard to objects.
Mind in regard to objects.
Yeah.
So, the I and the objects, there wouldn't be any space discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, obviously, there wouldn't be any seeing discerned, if there is no mind present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's that presence of the mind, that's what space is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'm having trouble on seeing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I can understand that no mind, no vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you don't have to see it elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, what you think now, that the space is, that's being discerned through your eye and the vision,
[SPEAKER_00]: Stay with that same space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, eh... just put it in the place of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't attribute it to the eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same thing that you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just assuming it at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the eye can only see, but the mind is what discloses here, yonder, in between?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, but see, even the eye can only see would... wouldn't make any sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't even think that if you can't think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's not being thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the senses without a mind are inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will not operate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's, you know, you won't find a space that's clearly defined phenomena in your mind, but what I'm explaining now might be enough, basically, to just sort of bring you back, like, just a couple of millimeters back, so to speak, which is enough to stop assuming and
[SPEAKER_00]: Rooting that space into the actual I and thoughts, means basically misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, that's why the mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although...
[SPEAKER_00]: is negative in regard to things that appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Structurally, it precedes things that appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Space or mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's... we're talking about space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you then discern that, that, okay, so space can't stand on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not misconceiving it as a separate, mystical, universal entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or some great providence of the divine nature or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You discern it as innate phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know that it comes structurally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simultaneously present with the things that have been seen, heard, touched, tasted, smelled, tasted and thought of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the space is simultaneously present with those things, but it structurally precedes them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is how people end up assuming that space and time are universal entities that we inhabit in.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, there is overshooting the mark.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you give it complete independence.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not independent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would not be discernible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Space, if there are no things that occupy space.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, there is a truth in it, in the sense that it is more primordial, structurally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not before, not after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that sense, it precedes, it comes first, and then everything else comes second.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your mind discerns that rightly, and establishes itself upon the phenomenon of space, then you really... then you can see, basically, how it will be withdrawn, the mind, from, eh... everything else that occupies that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you establish your mind on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... and such, eh... general negative phenomenon of space is infinite.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no cap to it that you can put on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just infinite.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the mind gets established upon that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it is established upon that, it can't possibly exercise or entertain any lust, aversion, delusion, in regard to anything that occupies that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's seen as circumstantial and risen.
[SPEAKER_02]: That infinity of space, that's...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going to go on a limb and say, that's not referring to like, oh, the universe is infinitely long.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, no, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's the... that's the projected, concealed space and time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are we saying when we're saying space, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are we saying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is space referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: I just want to... Space?
[SPEAKER_00]: Space.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is space between you and me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can you can particularize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say that there is also space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it shares the same nature as the general, you know, base of infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll have to think about that some more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, the mind needs to be trained in regard to it, because you don't want to make it into an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you, me,
[SPEAKER_00]: Two positives, uh, at a different angle of the spectrum, from this point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, where is the space now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you try to grasp the space in same positive terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You try to disclose it in the same manner you want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you'll disclose something, but there won't be the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you think that is that what space is, then you'll be seriously misconceiving it, or not finding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be seen as a peripheral phenomenon that structurally comes first, not temporally.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is meant when something structurally comes first?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means it's simultaneously present, but it's not second.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're saying you can have ideas of non-temporal with a first and a second?
[SPEAKER_00]: First and second, well, you can have this and this, but one of the this is the first this, the other one is the second this.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, one is more fundamental than the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does fundamental mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamental means, basically, it precedes the other one, in that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, imagine you have a line of people in front of you, or just two people in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're in the same line.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not left or right, not before or after.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're right there at the same time, but one of them is closer, the other one is... Closer, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a vertical point, not a linear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you said in the preface of the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I've already said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simultaneous presence of the two things, one is close to the other one isn't, but they're both simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that similar to, like, thinking of things as more external, less external?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is that a different kind of route?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a different route.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be a different route.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's deriving the same simultaneous principle of upādāna, but yeah, I wouldn't, I wouldn't try to
[SPEAKER_00]: I realized after I said it the other way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the first thing is the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always the first, most first, first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something like a place which has no vacancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, it's, they're things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it could be placed in space, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Space?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Space is a kind of... a place which... it places... it's like a place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, when you say place, people imagine an actual setup.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing, because the structure, the space is infinite, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why things are possible to arise on a particular level, on the basis of that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is of space and of time, not in space and in time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's made of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you want to think like that, because in that, when you, when you, when you think about mind, well, you won't make it mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll see it as part of the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, when you think about the space, scientific space, you won't make it into scientific space, because, you know, well, it wouldn't be there, because that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you divorce it, then, yes, you get the scientific space that we all inhabit, and you get this mind, mind inside of this head, inside of this brain, that nobody, that only me, knows and sees, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But space is of mind and of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in space and in time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It brings to mind, like, if you, you know, you get a lot of people, like, trying to organize their thoughts, and it almost feels like they're organizing things in space, like mental space.
Yeah, yeah.
A very mundane example, but sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: What also contributed to me starting to think in this way was, you know, I was observing a particular thought, let's say, and it's so easy to assume, like, oh, my thoughts are happening here, somewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where I got the thing, oh,
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how the mind can expand itself, in terms of the development, in terms of getting established upon a different basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you stop assuming it right here, in this head or whatever, whatever you end up assuming, because that's completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you're actually, you know, my thought cannot really be placed in this head.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's already quite a transcendental dimension that you were never aware of, yet it's a simple thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so the thought arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is real, it's phenomenal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: It persists while it's changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you can't put it in that space that you regard as space, usually, in a common sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the nature of perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with any of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because aggregates are not in space.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, the space is basically generated by the positioning of the five aggregates of the simultaneously present matter, feeling, perception, intentions and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't pinpoint, you can't say.
No, no, no, no.
Of course not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it perceives that designation of it's there, it's here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the five aggregates, then it's the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not one point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's five points of views.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, five domains, five heaps.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they're all called heaps.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't they?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just packed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, they're packed over each other, so to speak, but not... like, they don't mix, they don't merge, they don't start, they don't connect and morph into one mass.
[SPEAKER_00]: They remain fully distinct.
[SPEAKER_00]: And cannot possibly encroach into another domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already off-space.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I forget...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's off-space confusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said, in-space.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's giving the space the priority over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the ultimate development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the ultimate development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means space is secondary from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneous is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just not as close.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means all space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the space that you're thinking of, that you're seeing, in the established mindfulness of the experience as a whole, it's not, you know, that is the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to find the right, the correct space.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you have to do is stop assuming it as being ultimately the first, in the sense that everything is inside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just maintain the simultaneous presence of that phenomenon that seems secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like something's proceeding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, something's determining it, which is the final object, which is experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're resting on it together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's... they're both... they're resting together.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
No one says that the object's resting on it.
I don't mean that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like it's supported... it is supported by it, but equally supported.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I guess, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that will... if that will... if that will establish the simultaneous, um...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the person within us thinks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yeah, you can think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: The space is not on the same footing as if I were a gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in regard to them, but not them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very much like upādāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was going to say, where are these other things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, how can you... Well, think of it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you have a notion of space if you're not thinking it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's only present as a, no matter how ambiguous thought, still a thought, which means the mind does come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is off space.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't have the mind without a space.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mind is not in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even the ambiguous general mystical notion of just pure space, it's a notion, it's a thought, it's a reasoned dhamma that is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would not be the case if that genuine space would precede your thought and your thought would be in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, even that is actually inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you stop and think about it, even that misconception, it's it's kind of contradictory, because you can't even misconceive it, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, once you discern things, you can't undo the knowledge, because it just becomes incomprehensible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this particular sense, like you have now a notion that things are in space, but then
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole notion rests upon ignoring the fact that that space is also thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these thoughts are in the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's not, then, the space that I'm contributing it to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Between thoughts are thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, thoughts of space are thoughts of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't be thoughts in space, because there will be another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, saying that it's inaccessible means ceasing the assumption of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you know it becomes inaccessible, means you cannot access it through ignorance anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, it's basically, it cannot be assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, it's now
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot assume something when you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's involuntary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not an optional thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take any worldly assumption that you might have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I assume such places, such and such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you find out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go there and you see for yourself what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if your assumption was right, that assumption is gone now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you actually experienced it and seen it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you think about your past assumption, you cannot possibly revoke it, because now the knowledge is tightly fitted in the space where assumption... and there's no place for assumption to enter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, it becomes inaccessible to assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a big vision of space.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see space.
[SPEAKER_01]: All space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sighted space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: That space, whatever I perceive it as, as a thought, that's not the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all the space you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's either going to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no real space as opposed to space you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's only conceived space, or space free from conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, an assumed space, or space known for what it is, and not assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, you're trying to have both at the same time, and compare them, and see which one's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the vision of space, it's not technically of space, it's of things, that negatively reveal, or rather, show the space as there, as not things.
So, you're kind of saying that the difference is like, instead of saying this is in space, rather one should say there are things that disclose the presence of space.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that disclosed space is more fundamental in regard to those particular things that disclose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, from the point of view of the mind and the five aggregates, it isn't the ultimate fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said, if you use space in a way to practice contemplation in regard to particular things, that's fine, because basically that space will stand for the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to be careful not to develop views that you are somehow in this universal public space, and give it, like, and make it an entity, that it's independent of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to do that, well, then don't forget that the mind is the fundamental thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, what I'm saying, you can be... take particular things and then practice contemplation in regard to development of the mind, discerning of the nature of the thoughts in the mind and citta, because that already includes that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, all you want to do is develop, or rather discern, the principle between the actual and the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that actual is the sense object, peripheral will be space in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's fine, if you develop knowledge of the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start looking at that peripheral space as the actual, well, then mind will be peripheral in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five aggregates will be peripheral in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you develop, again, understanding of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you don't want to be discerning peripheral space in regard to things and then just assuming the same space that shares the same in regard to the mind as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're not developing principle of the simultaneous present.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not discerning it in regard to either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, space is always peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless when you think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can say something else is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means what you're thinking of is then not this misconceived space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you think of space where the space cannot be found.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, from the point of view of discerning the peripheral, it doesn't matter if you refer to it as space or as the mind, to the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how you refer to it, as long as it's seen as peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when you have a thought about space, then, you remain mindful in regard to peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remain mindful of the peripheral in regard to that thought, this is space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, soon enough, you'll see that that's not the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: The space is always on the peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, your experiences of space can be in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the space would mean, basically, when you would feel to give a complete independent
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, complete independence to the notion of actual thought space and then attribute even the peripheral to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, it's in the space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's a... that's a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a wrong assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you're saying, if I say something in space, it's assuming space was already kind of just there hanging out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have a thought, oh, the space, in the space, but don't give it that full independence and don't attribute that which is peripheral in regard to that thought, this space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't attribute the peripheral to it, as in everything is in the space, because that's completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no basis for that assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to discern space in the right terms, you know, you don't have to try to think it out, because it's pointless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just feel the feeling, perceive whatever is being perceived simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: That experience will be the experience of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that experience even precedes the craving that you have now to fit the space in the right terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it precedes the craving, then, well, it's... it's... it's fit in the right terms, not in your terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, then, any notions of... that you might have had then, before that, of, oh, space was this, space is that, it just becomes pointless.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, uh, irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm pointing out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to get out by thinking your way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to get out by seeing it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, accept it, that you have notions of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that's a present, that is an experience as a whole for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, in regard to that, feel the feelings, perceive those perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, uproot it with mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to figure it out and explain it to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it needs to be understood, and seen, and discerned, but it doesn't mean explain to yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's kind of why I wanted to understand something, but not necessarily be able to put it into words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means you did not quite understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you qualify it just as I said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explaining it to yourself is not the same as understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explaining it is finding a plausible explanation from the point of view that you still have.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I explained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's plausible to me now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the criteria of what's plausible or not, it's not fully developed, obviously, because otherwise you wouldn't be resorting to the temporal explanations of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're referring to is describing something once it has been understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's definitely not an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a description.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for throughout the description, the thing remains present because it's understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: In explanation, that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: In explanation, you might arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, so you think you arrived at it when you explained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that means you didn't have it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, how can you explain it if you don't have it to begin with?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, you want to replace explanations with descriptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Phenological descriptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what suttas are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Prescure descriptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nalu, second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, even the notion of peripheral is already a notion of expanse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Place as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, place.
[SPEAKER_00]: The expanse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is actual, and then the... everything else that's not there, it's already the expanse in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the space is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like foreground and background.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fairly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why... that's why you don't... that's what I mean, like, when you have... even if you have a thought of doubt, what is space then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Find peripheral in regard to that, and that's where the space is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it becomes impenetrable to doubt as well, because doubt can only be actual.
[SPEAKER_02]: Going back a bit, that whole thing we've just been talking about is... is the reason why we can also do... designate things like, oh, internal, external, that's also spatial.
Yes, yeah.
Basically, then, external would kind of naturally be attributed to anything that's sort of...
In space.
In space, actual, through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else, this whole, the expanse I was referring to, would be kind of this ambiguous internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when that's also seen as simultaneously present phenomenon, not as the sense object, obviously, but as that which pertains to the mind, then, yeah, either way, whether it's internal or external, are seen basically as external in regard to you, to your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, for the untrained mind, things around me that I can see, touch, taste, smell, taste, so on, those are the ones that I can access, that I can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's everything is external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that's not that is internal and I'm kind of in between and everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And usually, people are that, for them, their own thoughts are not even seen as something that exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: They clearly talk about what they think, but they will not regard it, they will not give it the same
[SPEAKER_00]: amount of existence as they would to the things that they can obtain through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind got so far out, proliferated towards the senses, that that became the threshold of what's real, what the being is, what the what the extent of the being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then everything under that threshold is just assumed to not exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although that's a contradiction in terms of
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can say this doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it clearly exists, because otherwise you couldn't refer to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you attribute non-existence to something that doesn't appear at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you attributed non-existence to something means it has appeared, which means it actually exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the same with mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it is, when it arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that's what that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't... Every reflection, every contemplation, having mentioned that in the last talk that I had with you, has to be rooted in the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be rooted there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That has to be the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about space on the basis of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not on the basis of your preconceived notion of the space that you had from before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You actually have to... You might feel the craving to, no, no, no, but I have to understand it on these terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's to say no to those terms, and re-establish the terms on the basis of the mindfulness of the experience as a whole, and then there, think about space, without losing that basis of that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, then you discern space within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't assume it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't fabricate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your path.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point of view that makes everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It reveals everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the eight points.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, as I said, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm pretty sure I mentioned it in that last thought as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to know what you're supposed to do with that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to know that that view is not the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That view, basically, is the view upon which you can develop discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That view is not discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The lens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a tool.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a tool, exactly, for seeing things through that lens.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for most people, mindfulness of experience is always the ultimate kind of culmination of the spiritual practice, whereby you just stay mindful in this pure, pristine awareness and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just stay mindful in your ignorance, because you're clearly not unraveling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, too much thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too much thinking, if you're thinking on a non-mindful base, then, yeah, you're just revolving around the same
[SPEAKER_00]: Same ignorance, same assumptions, and basically psychotherapeutizing your way out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explaining it to yourself, managing whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you establish the mindful base, or the mindfulness of the experience as a whole, then you can be all the thinking you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, it's the right mindful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the thinking, basically, it's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another thought for mental object is dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people either dismiss the thinking, as just thinking, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you know you're supposed to look for within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that by reading the sutras, by discerning the sutras, by investigating what they mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't tell you the answers by itself, which is what people think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just teach me, teach me what I need to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I heard it so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, yeah, right, ignorance will teach you what you need to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will teach you more ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, like, then you will naturally be free from saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's why you have to take up with any theoretical sub-sub-perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, instruction is the basis for contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of paticca-vāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of anything from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take your pick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what it is from the suttas, as long as it's fully understood from the basis of mindfulness of experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your vipassana, and that's your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's holding on the mindfulness while basically the right order of things being established through right thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know what this topic is,
[SPEAKER_02]: You've mentioned a lot of times the consciousness being like external with the objects, as opposed to thinking, oh, my conscious is here.
I was just kind of trying to think about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not to say that you didn't need the sense base for there to be... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, the problem...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I said that in a very well-defined context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that context was basically
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not on the level of objects that you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level where the matter is, because of which there are objects that you can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're not seeing the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when people don't know, when people still have assumption and conceiving that they're seeing that, which matter is, I'm looking at the cup and that's what the matter of the cup is, like I'm seeing the matter, I'm not seeing my perception, then they will think I'm just saying consciousness is out there with that cup.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: Could actually aid somebody in right thinking, even if they say it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they investigate it further, they'll find out, okay, surely it's not with the cup, but it's with the matter of the cup, which obviously I have perception in regard to, because of, but I can't perceive it, which means you can't even access consciousness by that, but it belongs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's oriented from the point of view of the matter, not from your point of view of the inside, or whatever you assume.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we, when you say that, that kind of gave me a spark, like, matter,
[SPEAKER_02]: It could be like, this matter, that matter, I'm not obviously designating what is actually matter, but, like, the base or the object, they're both matter.
The consciousness, you're saying, is on that level.
Yes.
Externally.
Yes, because that matter is external.
It constantly is bound with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that clarifies.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, I was thinking, like, are they really with the cup?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it would just be basically, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm sure there were views in philosophy that were just saying consciousness is out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I mean, my view, even in existentialism, Sartre was saying, but obviously, it was quite clear, that the way he would put it was, uh, intentionality is out there with the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, in a way, that's true, because then that out there, oh, that means basically this inside, this internal of me, becomes out there, becomes because of the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have these thoughts about, well, I'm going to do this and this and this with that, and that thing over there, only because those things are already given.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't need to be qualified, because then it's too easily assumed, or it's too complex to be just put in one sentence, without it being misunderstood by somebody who's coming from the point of view of the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't possibly just get that right.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think that cleared up
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, even saying, at the same time, also, it's not obviously the matter that's conscious, so to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
Consciousness that's conscious.
Exactly.
But they give need to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the that's the ultimate thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they really use the word juxtaposed when it came to consciousness and the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not even connected.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just placed side by side for no reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No reason to.
[SPEAKER_00]: No reason, no appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: No appropriation, no suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But like you need the I in a certain
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're saying they're a pair, but... Juxtaposed.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not on the same footing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not... they're just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, you don't think they're in space.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not sitting there next to each other on the front bench, talking to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's completely juxtaposed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everywhere and nowhere, so to speak, because you can't put it in space.
[SPEAKER_02]: What exactly is juxtaposed, as opposed to superimposed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, like superimposed kind of implies a direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Superimposed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Juxtaposed doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just placed side by side.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the result of that placement is the whole arising manifestation of the five aggregates, of the all of nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That placement is removed and you can't even conceive that juxtaposed relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can discern it rightly, but you can't, you know, you can't actually access it, because it's way below your feet and always moving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you recognize that the entire experience that you have
[SPEAKER_00]: As you just said, all you need to do is have your eyes removed, and it's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole domain of vision, everything you've ever seen, everything that you would have seen, everything that you experienced, any feelings that you experienced on account of things that you've seen, thoughts, plans, happiness, sadness, for eons and eons of lifetimes, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your eyes have been removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole vision is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But just the thing is, then you're reborn again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was using it as like a... just trying to get the terms straight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't even... you can't take possession of that relationship, which means you're just borrowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just... you're just basically a...
[SPEAKER_00]: A user of that which doesn't belong to you, yet you use it as if it is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eyes, nose, ears, tongue, body, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that because of which those things are, you can't possibly access, or have, or influence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just completely inaccessible from every direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just referring to the actual, the whole, the circumstantial nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inaccessible, which means all you know is it's not going to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, but it's not going to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to overshoot the mark, but you certainly must not undershoot it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by that I mean, you don't want to start conceiving the axis to that because of which your vision is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that because of which your smell, taste, sounds, touch, thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not conceiving the axis, you stop maintaining the wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, in the seeing, there is just the seeing, in the hearing, there is just the hearing, and so on.
So, just to clarify, my own head is going to be repeating probably things.
No, that's fine.
Matter and consciousness paired, but entirely, like, different.
Not connected.
But it's there.
Like, they're paired together, but not connected.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, like, just happens to be in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: A result of the complete circumstantial juxtaposing is your whole existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it always was, no matter of the realm, no matter of the river.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was always the case for devas, for animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody's exempt from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's completely circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel like you could drill some with that, but still have plenty of, like, assumptions about other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you just need to drill longer, until it saturates everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Likewise, matter and consciousness, they both don't appear either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't say consciousness without consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, even that got me thinking, like, oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that, you know, that's what I meant when, before, I said, for many times, my people use the word consciousness, you know, every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, call it my consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many of them, including yourself, do you know, what do you refer to when you say consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fire?
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarify.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said in the Sutra so many times, don't deem anything untermed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Investigate the meaning, interrogate yourself, until things are clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, not for the purpose of intellectual satisfaction, but for the purpose of full freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if this self-interrogation and investigating the meaning is done on the basis of the mindfulness of the experience as a whole,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the knowledge will result in freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be any other way.
Could we say that we can discern consciousness because things appear?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, we can't see it, but we can know that it's there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's very important that, no matter what contemplation you're doing, writing it down, thinking and pondering, to do it on the basis of the mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
And that can be kind of established on almost anything, generally, be it just certain things within whatever it might be.
Sure.
As long as you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Postures, mind, body, feel.
All of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm just here, present in this room, on top of a hill, in the central province, on the island, surrounded by the ocean, on the planet Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all true.
[SPEAKER_00]: In space.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the universe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Using this word.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the expanse.
And the personal general does... it does appear, not like consciousness.
Is that true?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, peripheral appears to a lesser intensity of the actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's different than the relation between consciousness and other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The consciousness is the direction from which, where, peripheral is then found.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the ultimate peripheral is the peripheral that doesn't appear, which is peripheral of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ultimate negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: When we establish the awareness of something peripheral, that is, in a mindful way, it's not the same thing as just completely forgetting about it.
Right?
It still has to be there to some degree, but then there's...
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's how mindfulness is properly established, peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual mindfulness is not mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going...
[SPEAKER_00]: So the mindfulness is... That's where mindfulness is established, on the peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, people who are not aware of peripheral are not mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's still kept in mind, even though it's peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't... you don't need to keep the peripheral in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, by discerning it, you become mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing the peripheral, you become mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You become unknowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be doing it in the beginning, because you don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you try to do it, which is a form of doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, by discerning the peripheral, you are mindful of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simply by knowing the peripheral, while the actual is present, you're mindful of the actual.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I'm sitting, I'm sitting in the kundi, because you could think of that as like
[SPEAKER_02]: Look at that peripherally.
When you're saying actual, it's not like actual versus imaginary, like both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's present peripherally, like I'm in Kuti.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in a sense of imaginary, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, you're thinking, I'm here, I'm sitting on the chair now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to sit on this chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actual kundalini.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's in front?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's basically where you were attending right there, right now, in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the presence of the chair, the presence of your body, the bodily posture, the room, the empty room, the room occupied by people, the hill, the element of earth, all those peripheral that your mind can discern and become established upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that doesn't mean you become completely oblivious to the actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, doesn't mean you make that new peripheral
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you make that peripheral a new actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you're mindful of that peripheral in regard to whatever happened to be actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it's that relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two simultaneous to present things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral and actual.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think you could actually even forget the actual entirely.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be an actual of some sort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you recognize that you can't forget it,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the eh... the unremitting mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even the act of forgetting, you're mindful of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the act of remembering, you're mindful of.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's... there's nowhere anymore any induction of ignorance in regard to those things, because it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always going to be that 1% of either actual or at least 1% of either peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of 100% of all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that 1% is more than enough for the full establishment of mindfulness.